<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Settle Gliese Developer Blog</title>
    <description>The developer blog for Settle Gliese
</description>
    <link>http://blog.settle-gliese.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://blog.settle-gliese.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jun 2022 18:28:54 +0200</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 24 Jun 2022 18:28:54 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.2.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Cramped Apartments and Space Stations</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-settle-gliese-backstory&quot;&gt;The Settle Gliese Backstory&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Settle Gliese is set in a dystopian future where most inhabitants on earth are kept in dingy apartments with nothing to do except play on their computers and watch TV all day. Some of these understandably bored individuals find themselves targeted by adverts that offer a way out. They are tempted into joining a twisted gameshow - one in which they’re transported to a terraformed planet and dropped off with no supplies, all for the entertainment of people back on earth. It’s the most ambitious and expensive reality TV show ever, organised by one of the megacorporations that controls all of the resources and factories. How will the people get on in the new planet? Will they learn to work together and form a better society than the one they left behind? Or will the desperations of a life without modern comforts drive them towards violence? And what about this shadowy megacorp? What do the people working for them think about all this? And how exactly did they manage to terraform this planet just for entertainment purposes?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re trying to introduce the player into this world and get them asking these questions as they play through the tutorial. One way we’re achieving this is through the size and shape of the rooms - we want small, cramped rooms connected with long tight corridors. Another vital part is of course the pixel art. This week I’ve been integrating the new pixel art into the tutorial, and I’m very pleased with the result so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-dingy-apartment&quot;&gt;The Dingy Apartment&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/bedroom.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;You don’t want to know where the toilet is…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The apartment is very small and you can’t see anything outside it. The door looks very heavy and the player is unable to walk through it. The chair in the apartment doubles as storage, which is a smart design choice in such a tiny room. There is nothing for the player to do except start up his computer and browse aimlessly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-space-station&quot;&gt;The Space Station&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/spaceship.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Who would’ve thought an office floating in space could be so boring?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The space station has long bare corridors and spartan offices. It is a bit tired looking, with little notes stuck up in front of some of the office doors. You can see some barrels and pipes attached to the outer hull in silhouette - clearly it was built without beauty in mind. Like in any corporation, there seems to be a hierarchy here. Some of the people you talk to go to lengths to show you they are more important than you, whereas others seem to be more friendly and less formal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/choose-embark.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Whatever architect designed this place needs a paycut&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-shuttle&quot;&gt;The Shuttle&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/spacepod.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey, you look like someone I know…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The shuttle taking you to the planet is small and clunky looking - it is more cube shaped than the sleek rocket designs of earlier space shuttles. Here you will meet your comrades if you choose to embark somewhere new.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, that about  sums up what I’ve been working on this week - now let’s hear from our guest writer, who has been labouring under a hot Berlin sun (I let them pick their own title for their section this week…)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bloggy-bit-sry-its-not-much-i-cant-think-of-anything-else-to-say-cos-hot&quot;&gt;bloggy bit sry it’s not much, i can’t think of anything else to say cos hot&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hello from your local pixel artist! I have been busy these weeks working on some of the rarer and more far-flung flora and fauna on Gliese. The places that won’t make up the majority of arable land but will hopefully be special places to travel through and explore. I kind of don’t want to spoil these locations (and you’d want to chart biomes like “The Slimes”, “Crunchy Forest” and “Gumbo Rumblings” yourself right?) so today instead I’ll share some rejected pixel art.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/experimentbloggy.png&quot; width=&quot;340&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Okay, who keeps putting holes in my dang fences?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something we wanted to explore with what’s possible to make in Gliese is limitations that resources would have on what you make and how it looks. Regionally accessible dyestuffs for example could tell the story of how far you had to travel and how many friends you had to make along the way to have your fancy blue and yellow fence for example. And as you travel you can expect to run into different cultures and architecture arising from different locations. The above ideas were initial explorations of this idea but weren’t in keeping with the style we are going for so we won’t be using them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I leave you with these &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nationalgeographic.com/magazine/article/searching-for-californias-mysterious-albino-redwood&quot;&gt;gorgeous albino pines&lt;/a&gt; photographed by Natgeo. While you’re out there exploring Gliese keep an eye out for these arboreal ghosts&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s all for this week folks! Check in next time when I’ll introduce you to the wonderful world of procedural world generation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jun 2022 16:00:36 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://blog.settle-gliese.com/2022/06/24/cramped-apartments-and-space-stations.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.settle-gliese.com/2022/06/24/cramped-apartments-and-space-stations.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Journeying to Gliese</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;lets-journey-together&quot;&gt;Let’s Journey Together&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hello again friends. This week work continued on the tutorial. I hope to have most of the functionality finished by the end of next week so I can start on the fun stuff - generating the beautiful new biomes, animals, and tech tree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;graceful-long-potato-shaped-people&quot;&gt;Graceful Long Potato Shaped People&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One important but slightly problematic task I did this week was converting the current game engine from 16px square tiles to 16px x 24px rectangles. Unfortunately I’m still loading in the old tileset because the new one is not ready, which has lead to this interesting ‘stretched potato person’ effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/stretched-potato.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Is it just me or is something strange happening?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;space-tiles&quot;&gt;Space tiles&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next week I will try to replace these glorious stretched potatos with something from the new artwork. Check out these tiles we’ve been creating&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/walls.png&quot; width=&quot;200&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Walls of various sorts&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The space station will be owned and operated by a mega corporation, who are sadistically sending you to the planet for their latest reality TV show. We want the space station to strike a balance between ‘futuristic cutting-edge technology’ and ‘shabby souless corporate office’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/tileset-ship.png&quot; width=&quot;220&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Space walls and silhouetted space station parts&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;draggable-grid-layout&quot;&gt;Draggable Grid Layout&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/transport-tycoon.jpeg&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Transport tycoon was an early adopter of this revolutionary layout style&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am toying with the idea of making the various screens in the game draggable, resizable, and hide-able. Depending on what is happening in the game you might want a few different menus up. When in a deep conversation, for example, you might want a small game screen and an enlarged dialogue screen; when you’re crafting it can be helpful to have your inventory and the crafting screen both showing; and so on. Let me know what you think of this idea in the discord.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/draggable-grid.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A draggable grid offers the most layout flexibility&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conversation-trees&quot;&gt;Conversation Trees&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you first arrive on the space station orbiting the planet Gliese, you have a conversation with the captain, who fills you in on what you’ll be getting up to when you arrive on the planet. We need more versatile ways for characters to communicate asyncronously, and allowing players to create their own dialogue trees would be one way to accomplish this, so this screen may be used for more than just the tutorial. In the future I will remove the purple and orange boxes from the dialogue and go with a more dignified white-on-black design. Adding some logic to convert *asterisks* to &lt;em&gt;italic&lt;/em&gt; would be a nice improvement as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/dialogue-tree.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A conversation between a new recruit and the captain of the space station&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;generated-embark-lobby&quot;&gt;Generated Embark Lobby&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once a character has been introduced to the world by the captain of the space station, they will be sent off to either join an existing group of established settlers or, if they are feeling particularly reckless, a new group. Rather than displaying a static menu showing which groups are available, I thought it would be more fun to generate rooms for the player to join. There will be a control panel in each room that will show a descripition of the group you are considering joining, and some furniture and decorations. The rooms will be sized according to how many players are currently in the group. Players on the planet will be able to edit their control panel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/embark-lobby.png&quot; height=&quot;650&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This wooden space station with beautiful sand flooring is only temporary&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;embark-options&quot;&gt;Embark Options&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a character is ambitious, the option is open for them to create their own embark group. The creator will have the chance to choose the biome the embark group joins, and give a brief description in which they can describe their goals for the group. It would also be useful for the creator to specify how close to other groups they would like to be - some groups might like the challenge of being completely isolated, whereas others will aim to establish relationships with nearby groups as quickly as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/create-embark-group.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A new embark group form&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another option is to show the user the full map of the planet and highlight which areas fit their current search parameters - if that’s done, users could even choose a specific place to embark to. I’m a little reluctant to do that, however, because the idea of players not knowing the world map and having to discover it as a player group appeals to me. It would also be open to abuse from griefers and metagamers. Let me know what you would rather have in the discord channel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading folks, I’ll see you again next week!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jun 2022 12:20:37 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://blog.settle-gliese.com/2022/06/16/embarking-to-gliese.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.settle-gliese.com/2022/06/16/embarking-to-gliese.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Growing Gliese’s Forests, From the Roots Up</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;this-weeks-update&quot;&gt;This Week’s Update&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hello friends and welcome to this week’s update. The true work has started in earnest now and I’ve started on an exciting and vital aspect of the game world. Read on to find out what - but first, the next section will be guest written by our talented pixel artist auilix&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;growing-glieses-forests-from-the-roots-up&quot;&gt;Growing Gliese’s Forests, From the Roots Up&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/early-pixel-art.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The forests of the artist’s youth&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I admit, I thought that developing the forests of a planet through pixel art would be an easy first step into Settle Gliese’s generated alien world. I love trees and the comfort of forests and, armed with references and scholarly articles (check out these &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.indefenseofplants.com/blog/2017/10/31/the-first-trees-ripped-themselves-apart-to-grow&quot;&gt;prehistoric trees&lt;/a&gt;!, I started off emulating tilesets of the trees from games gone by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/side-view.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Ah, repeating tree tiles as far as they eye can see&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going in this direction was hearkening back to my own history with older consoles and JRPGs but was quite out of touch with the built up history of roguelikes and their much more constrained visual language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/roguelike.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The original Rogue (1980)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/dwarf-fortress.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A forest in Dwarf Fortress (2002)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even modern roguelikes tend to use limited sprites or ASCII art to evoke their worlds and inhabitants, resulting in a unique look and mood. With this in mind, I turned towards pictographic and logographic languages as an inspiration and began to draw up more conceptual representations of trees. Deconstructing trees and pushing symbolic meaning in the limited constraints of 16 x 24 pixel tiles let to some crop circle-ish results:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/iconic.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The top right tree partially inspired by a blanket my mom crocheted for me&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think my personal favourite of this series was on the middle row on the right which looks like it could be related to the Nazca geoglyphs of South America. Though these trees were recognisable enough, the main problem was that they’d be too limited in scope to be able to express Settle Gliese’s 40+ different planned biomes with that much diversity. So it was back to the Aesprite board to develop something both symbolic but not too pared down, with room for lots of biodiversity and personality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/final.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Please excuse the in-development wanderers who are modelling the forest for us&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These circuit board-esque trees hit the right spot for us. They look like they could be of some future age while at the same time wouldn’t look that out of place on an illuminated manuscript. And their complexity feels right for the look and feel of changing regions as you move throughout the world, while not straying too far from the look of its genre. The next step for me will be expanding this design to flora and fauna and fully visualising Gliese’s first biomes. More on that soon!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introducing-players-to-the-world&quot;&gt;Introducing Players to the World&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for that, auilix! Whilst they’ve been busy working on that, I can share for the first time in a world exclusive what exciting things I’ve been working on this week. That’s right guys - it’s the tutorial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://giphy.com/embed/nbNWgtnMgIYpUSy3e9&quot; width=&quot;480&quot; height=&quot;327&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;giphy-embed&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://giphy.com/gifs/fallontonight-jimmy-fallon-tonight-show-nbNWgtnMgIYpUSy3e9&quot;&gt;via GIPHY&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps not the most thrilling for the readers of this blog, but an important part of the game. In the alpha, you were simply dropped on an alien planet and left to get on with things. Lots of players, especially those new to the text based roleplaying genre, would simply run off into the wilderness before speaking to anyone and get lost out there until they inevitably starved to death. I decided to provide some context to the game to help new playeres out - maybe they will still run off into the wild with their first character, but they will at least understand what they should be trying to do when creating their second. Rather than just show them a wall of text, I decided an interactive tutorial might be more entertaining. I’m about halfway done with it, and wanted to share my progress with you dear reader. The artwork is not ready so you’ll have to use your imagination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/startup.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When you first start a new game, you will find your character alone in a tiny apartment here on earth&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/startup.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The door will be locked. Eventually you will figure out the only thing you can do is sit at your desk and turn your computer on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/pong.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;For a while, you will entertain yourself by playing pong, or perhaps some other moderately entertaining task&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/informatic.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/informatic.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Click on the image to see it full size&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then you will be interrupted with an advert. If you press escape, you can return to the safety of your apartment. But for those brave (or bored) enough to press any key, will be taken to the ‘registration form’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/registration.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/registration.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A fully filled out registration form. Click on the image again to see it full size&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This page is intended to get players thinking about the personality of their character. Players new to text based roleplaying games tend to invent flawless individuals which can be uninteresting to interact with, so I have included some questions like ‘what are your weaknesses’ to guide these players towards making more nuanced characters. I had great fun randomly generating answers. Once this page is filled out, you are taken to a spaceship en route to the planet, where you will be shown a bit more about the world, and choose who to embark with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me know what you think about the character creation page - if you have any good answers to the questions, they’ll be added to the auto generator and appear in the final game!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next week I’ll be working on what happens when you’ve submitted your form and find yourself on a spaceship heading straight for the planet Gliese. You’ll meet a couple of interesting characters who explain the strange world you’ve found yourself in further.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jun 2022 14:56:46 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://blog.settle-gliese.com/2022/06/05/growing-glieses-forests.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.settle-gliese.com/2022/06/05/growing-glieses-forests.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How to Generate a World</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;this-weeks-update&quot;&gt;This Week’s Update&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hello friends. This week has been a pretty exciting time for the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First but by no means least, after some months of paperwork ping pong I have received the contract for the funding application, so fingers crossed I might actually receive the first installment some time soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For most of the week I’ve been working on the prologue, which has involved building a terminal emulator, and building a sort of ‘staged scene’ in the game world. There’s still plenty of work to do here but it’s been fun getting my hands dirty. I’ll try not to show too many spoilers, but here’s one little screen shot which doesn’t give too much away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/terminal.png&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Now you too, can be a hacker&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pixel-art&quot;&gt;Pixel Art&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/warmup-septembitchall.png&quot; height=&quot;300&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Some pink items&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/warmup-froggypractice.png&quot; height=&quot;192&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Various frogs of different types&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Auilix, the pixel artist (follow them &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/auilix&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;), started off the week getting into pixel art. Drawing on a small top-down scale with a limited palette is more puzzle working and problem solving than illustration usually is, so warm ups are necessary. Saultoon’s excellent &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/c/saultoons&quot;&gt;channel&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/septembit&quot;&gt;Septembit challenge&lt;/a&gt; were a perfect jumping-off point and check out these 16 x 16 frogs as a bonus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After some design exploration and palette building, we decided to go with a rectangular 16 x 24 pixel tile over the 16 x 16 tiles we used in the alpha for Settle Gliese. A vertical rectangle shape is more ‘human’ shaped than a square, and I think it makes the sprites seem more mature and less potato shaped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/pixelexperiments1a.png&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Potato people and square objects&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/pixelexperiments2a.png&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Long graceful, people-shaped people&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a consequence there will be more tiles on a panel, which I don’t think is a bad thing. Let me know what you think!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And for all you dead by daylight fans, here is some dead by daylight fan art in the new style:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/lildbd.png&quot; height=&quot;72&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Coming soon to a screen near you - Dead By Daylight the Roguelike&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;game-design&quot;&gt;Game Design&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve also been working a lot on the game design and have made some pretty big decisions that I think will improve how the game plays. There’s still a lot that will go into this and everything’s a work in progress. If you have any thoughts or suggestions about these feel free to share in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://discord.gg/h9sCtUfhhW&quot;&gt;discord&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mountains-into-mazes&quot;&gt;Mountains into Mazes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mountains represented a serious barrier for early humans, and impeded migration to such an extent that in some places different cultures, languages, and even races would develop on either side of the mountain range. Pretty cool, right? I want this to arise in the game, but how to achieve this in an interesting way? We could always force characters to move very slowly through mountain regions, or add a chance of them dying, but I wanted characters to feel that desperation of being lost and stuck halfway up a mountain and these options didn’t quite give that feeling. But I had another idea - we could turn the mountains into huge multi-panel mazes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/maze-mountain.png&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;What a maze looks like&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this way players can cross if they’re really desperate, brave, or foolish, but I hope most players will be sufficiently put off. Hopefully this is a nice way of translating a real world problem into a ‘game-like’ problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mines-into-dungeons&quot;&gt;Mines into Dungeons&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mines were also very dangerous places back in the day, so much so that the best way to get rich from mining was to persuade someone else to do it for you. In the alpha of the game mining was simply a case of walking up to a deposit of some stone or ore, and clicking the ‘gather’ button.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/alpha-mine.png&quot; height=&quot;150&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;An familiar scene&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted it to be more dangerous, to force players to make the same kind of risk reward calculations that early humans must have considered when entering a mine. My first idea was to make players ‘dig’ a mine, and on each dig there was a percentage chance of the mine collapsing and the player dying. Then I realised what countless other game designers must have realised before me, we can represent the danger of a mine in a much more entertaining way by turning them into dungeons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/mock-mine.png&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A very bare bones mock up of a mine-dungeon&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A player can enter a mine and battle their way through monsters if they want to find the riches buried therein. Or if they value their life, they can persuade other players to explore the mines for them. I hope this will be a nice system for giving newspawns a fun task, as town leaders can persuade them to go spelunking on their behalf.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;multiple-metals&quot;&gt;Multiple Metals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A final problem I had with the alpha was that once you had discovered bronze and made all bronze items, there wasn’t much further tech tree to go, but before you discovered bronze there also wasn’t much to do. My first thought was to simply make discovering bronze harder and expand the early game tech tree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/scrap-metal.jpeg&quot; height=&quot;300&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A bunch of useless metal&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I think a better solution is to have multiple new metals made up of two or more ores, with varying rarity. The rarer metals will of course produce to stronger weapons, armour, and tools. This I think should be a lot easier to balance than the ‘just bronze’ route, and with the best of metals only available if you mine ores coming from opposite sides of the planet, it will strongly incentivise long trade routes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;apothecaries-and-brainchip-upgrades&quot;&gt;Apothecaries and Brainchip Upgrades&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as metals, we can apply a similar principle to the creation of tonics and the upgrading of brainchips. Local plants or rare minerals can provide small upgrades, but for the most powerful effects you’ll need to swap plants that only occur on the other side of the planet. With plants, players will need ‘local knowledge’ - you can only harvest the valuable parts of the plant if you were born in that region. In this way long distance trade or tyranical empires will be the only methods of obtaining the most powerful in game items.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-generate-a-planet&quot;&gt;How to Generate a Planet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of you may be interested in how the planet Gliese was generated, so I will add a quick lowdown of how I did it here. In summary - someone else did it for me. I used the brilliant open source project &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Mindwerks/worldengine&quot;&gt;Mindwerks WorldEngine&lt;/a&gt;, which generates a full little world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ancient_map_seed1.png&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The worlds are generated using plate techtonics, erosion, rain shadows, holdridge life zone models (whatever they are) and more.  I generated a number of little worlds until I found one I liked the look of. You choose the size of the world, and it generates elevation, precipitation, temperature, biome, and ocean maps as images. I then wrote a small program which reads each of these images and saves the data into a database. Not sure what I mean by that? Take for example this heat map&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/heat-map.png&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The average temperatures of a generated planet&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are seven colours on this map which represent seven temperatures. My program would look at each pixel, convert its colour into the temperature range (from 1-7), and save this data under the pixel’s position. Once I’d done this for every pixel, I had the full world in a database. Each of those pixels is one panel in Settle Gliese. Generating the terrain for the panels, including cliffs, rivers, and coastlines, was a little more complicated. Maybe I’ll write some more about that another time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading, I’ll see you again next week!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jun 2022 14:56:46 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://blog.settle-gliese.com/2022/06/05/how-to-generate-a-world.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.settle-gliese.com/2022/06/05/how-to-generate-a-world.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A World in a Petri Dish</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;hello-world&quot;&gt;Hello World&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcome to the Settle Gliese developer blog! I’ll be sharing my thoughts about Settle Gliese and let you know how development is going. I thought I’d start with some beard stroking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/my-beard.jpeg&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The author’s beard&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week I’ll be writing about how the game Settle Gliese will finally put to rest an age old philosophical question - how did we go from a hunter gatherer lifestyle to the more technologically advanced ones you see today?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-mute-ages&quot;&gt;The Mute Ages&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Modern humans have existed for somewhere between 200,000 and 300,000 years. Strangely, some people think we only actually learned to speak 50,000 years ago, so for that first 150,000 years or so we were just standing around looking at each other, and thinking to ourselves how useful it would be to communicate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/confused.webp&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;What it would be like if we couldn’t speak&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;technology-victory&quot;&gt;Technology Victory&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we did get language figured out, it was still not an easy road to the wonders of the modern age. Shockingly, things did not really get started until we learned the basics of agriculture just 12,000 years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Agriculture was the key&lt;/strong&gt; that unlocked the human technology tree, because before we stayed in one place farming year round, we weren’t such a sitting target for maraudering rapists, so we didn’t need to bother inventing walls, swords, and shields - we could just run away. And we didn’t need things like massive clay pots or buildings for storage, because we just ate food as we got it instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how could it possibly take the (allegedly) smartest animal on earth 38,000 years just to figure out how to plant a seed in the ground and start up a nascent civilisation? How? Tell me, goddamnit!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-first-king---nasty-brutish-and-short&quot;&gt;The First King - Nasty, Brutish, and Short&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, like all unanswerable questions, this one has been answered by philosophers - a clever group of people that worked out they could just make stuff up and if nobody could prove them wrong, they could fool a university into hiring them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first of these great philosophers to answer this particular riddle (or at least the first I’ll be mentioning in this blog post) was none other than Thomas Hobbes. Born in 1588 in England, Thomas Hobbes was a teacher, so he had lots of practise making up the answers to things in order to seem clever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/hobbes.jpeg&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Thomas Hobbes was also nasty brutish and short&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1651 he published his book ‘Leviathan’, in which he argues that for that period of time before men formed themselves into civilisations, they spent all time team killing each other, stealing sex, and eating mud. It was a brutal time according to Hobbes, who famously described it as ‘solitary, poor, nasty, brutish, and short’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then one day, somewhere out in the killing fields, came a great figure, chosen by God to forge order out of the chaos. He marched around with a big stick and forced everyone to stop killing each other and jolly well behave themselves. He made some of them farm, others mine for minerals, and others made useful tools in exchange for food and minerals. And things just sort of snowballed from there. And that man’s name? Well, actually we don’t know his name, because he made everyone else call him ‘Your Majesty’ - he was the first king.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s Hobbes’s great explanation for how the first societies formed, and if he’s right, then we have a lot to thank that first king for. Sure, the simple days of sexing, killing, and eating weren’t all bad, but they were a darn sight worse than what we have now. And if we were dropped on an alien planet with no knoweldge of our previous lives on earth, according to Hobbes, we would return to that primitive state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-garden-of-eden&quot;&gt;The Garden of Eden&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But was it really all that bad? Or was Thomas Hobbes, the esteemed philosopher, just talking out of his bum hole all along? That’s what Jean-Jacques argued. Who? Why, Jean-Jacques Rousseau, of course!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/rousseau.jpeg&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Rousseau 1712-1778. Significantly less brutish than Hobbes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like all good Frenchmen, Rousseau &lt;em&gt;hated&lt;/em&gt; kings. So when he read about Thomas Hobbes’s story of the origin of civilisation, he just couldn’t be having that. Rousseau argued instead that life before civilisation was way &lt;em&gt;better&lt;/em&gt; than what came after it - after all, why else would we spend so long doing nothing but not-inventing-civilisation? The time before civilisation was a utopia. Men and women loved one another freely, young children skipped around gailey through fields of untended grass, we ate ripe fruit from trees, and all in all there was very little killing. Perhaps some of the only people to be killed at this time were the ones who had the gall to attempt to force us into civilisation. Rousseau wrote -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The first man who, having fenced in a piece of land, said ‘This is mine’, and found people naïve enough to believe him, that man was the true founder of civil society. From how many crimes, wars, and murders, from how many horrors and misfortunes might not any one have saved mankind, by pulling up the stakes, or filling up the ditch, and crying to his fellows: Beware of listening to this impostor; you are undone if you once forget that the fruits of the earth belong to us all, and the earth itself to nobody.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;necessity-is-the-mother-of-all-invention&quot;&gt;Necessity is the Mother of All Invention&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So who was right? Hobbes? Rousseau? Or is there another explanation? Perhaps agriculture was invented out of necessity, because there were simply too many of us to be able to sustain ourselves from hunting and gathering alone? One theory is that we liked to gather in huge numbers by large rocks stacked on end. We did this for religious reasons, and also to party, and these sites became so popular it was necessary to invent farming and other grown-up things like taxes to allow people to live there year round looking after the things. Well, that could be the case, but it seems like there are still a lot of smart people arguing about which theory is right to this day, and as more archaeological evidence comes out, the popular explanation keeps changing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-world-in-a-petri-dish&quot;&gt;A World in a Petri Dish&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In episode 154 of the Simpsons, Lisa places a tooth in a petri dish covered in cola for a school project. A spark of electricity hits the tooth, and by some mysterious querk or magic, life is formed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/lisa.webp&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The spark of life&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lisa watches through a microscope as mould forms, then is astonished as the mould turns into little tiny humans, first they are hunters, next they form agricultural communities, and before long they have a little world as rich and as complex as earth. If only Lisa watched a little closer, we’d have the answer to our question, of how and why civilisation was formed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;finally-an-answer---and-its-a-game&quot;&gt;Finally, an answer - and it’s a game!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, my friends, that brings us to Settle Gliese. Settle Gliese is a game about what would happen if you dropped a bunch of strangers in the middle of an untamed world, and watched how they get along. We’ll be able to see in real time, which ones are killing each other and eating mud, which ones are getting along famously, and which ones are running out of food and forced to settle down and start tending plants. It’s my hope that in time civilisation will spawn, and art, culture, trade, and emergent complexity is formed from the wilderness of the planet Gliese. The great debate will be settled once and for all. Or, well, in actual fact you probably shouldn’t really use this game to settle any debates. But at least it’ll be interesting to watch, and each of us can take part in a grand experiment to see how society was formed.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 28 May 2022 18:24:55 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://blog.settle-gliese.com/2022/05/28/a-world-in-a-petris-dish.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.settle-gliese.com/2022/05/28/a-world-in-a-petris-dish.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
