<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Settle Gliese Developer Blog</title>
    <description>The developer blog for Settle Gliese
</description>
    <link>http://blog.settle-gliese.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://blog.settle-gliese.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 13 Dec 2022 17:52:21 +0100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 13 Dec 2022 17:52:21 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.2.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Christmas Update</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Yo ho ho to all the good people of the internet. I’m sure you’ve all been asking yourselves what the latest progress is with Settle Gliese so here I am to provide you with an update.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;descriptions&quot;&gt;Descriptions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a great time twiddling around with some openAI text generation and have generated a huge amount of descriptions for all the plants and animals in the game. I have ambitions to extend these to man-made items as well - anything that you can add a description to can have an auto-generated description if you are lacking the inspiration or imagination to come up with your own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/camel.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A friendly camel&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/night-stalker.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A typically voluptuous beast&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;culture-specific-items&quot;&gt;Culture specific items&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All kinds of things now look differently depending on which of the eight cultures you are a part of. If you want the cool pot of the desert people but you are but a lowly swamp person, you’ll have no choice but to trade for it or steal it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/polar-community.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A polar community&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tents&quot;&gt;Tents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For any people that want to be nomads, there are a number of interesting tents and temporary structures they can utilise. Animals will not enter a tent so you can camp out in one safely as night falls. They can be taken down and carried on the back of a person or beast of burden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/tent.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A traditional goati tent&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tech-tree&quot;&gt;Tech Tree&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve ‘finalised’ the tech tree for now and added recipes and workshops for every item in the game. There’s a bunch of cool things in there such as special pots which can imbue your food with powers, brainchip enhancements, wagonways, sailing boats, guard houses, vending machines, and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;performance&quot;&gt;Performance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve improved the performance of the game by reducing the amount of data that needs to be saved and sent when you’re walking around the world. There’s still plenty of work to be done but I managed to reduce the database size by a factor of ten in the last couple of months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/riverside.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An unoptimised river&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;[
    { tileType: &apos;NONE&apos; }, { tileType: &apos;NONE&apos; }, { tileType: &apos;NONE&apos; }, { tileType: &apos;RIVER&apos; }, { tileType: &apos;NONE&apos; }, { tileType: &apos;NONE&apos; }, { tileType: &apos;NONE&apos; },
    { tileType: &apos;NONE&apos; }, { tileType: &apos;NONE&apos; }, { tileType: &apos;NONE&apos; }, { tileType: &apos;RIVER&apos; }, { tileType: &apos;NONE&apos; }, { tileType: &apos;NONE&apos; }, { tileType: &apos;NONE&apos; },
    { tileType: &apos;NONE&apos; }, { tileType: &apos;NONE&apos; }, { tileType: &apos;NONE&apos; }, { tileType: &apos;RIVER&apos; }, { tileType: &apos;NONE&apos; }, { tileType: &apos;NONE&apos; }, { tileType: &apos;NONE&apos; },
    { tileType: &apos;NONE&apos; }, { tileType: &apos;NONE&apos; }, { tileType: &apos;NONE&apos; }, { tileType: &apos;RIVER&apos; }, { tileType: &apos;RIVER&apos; }, { tileType: &apos;RIVER&apos; }, { tileType: &apos;NONE&apos; },
    { tileType: &apos;NONE&apos; }, { tileType: &apos;NONE&apos; }, { tileType: &apos;NONE&apos; }, { tileType: &apos;NONE&apos; }, { tileType: &apos;NONE&apos; }, { tileType: &apos;RIVER&apos; }, { tileType: &apos;NONE&apos; },
    { tileType: &apos;NONE&apos; }, { tileType: &apos;NONE&apos; }, { tileType: &apos;NONE&apos; }, { tileType: &apos;NONE&apos; }, { tileType: &apos;NONE&apos; }, { tileType: &apos;RIVER&apos; }, { tileType: &apos;NONE&apos; },
]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Converts nicely into an array of ones and zeros&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;[
    0, 0, 0, 1, 0, 0, 0,
    0, 0, 0, 1, 0, 0, 0,
    0, 0, 0, 1, 0, 0, 0,
    0, 0, 0, 1, 1, 1, 0,
    0, 0, 0, 0, 0, 1, 0,
    0, 0, 0, 0, 0, 1, 0,
]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which can be converted to a binary number &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;000100000010000001000000111000000100000010&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which can be converted to a hex number &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;4081038102&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which takes up a lot less space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;whats-next&quot;&gt;What’s Next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trailer will be out soon. Most of the major features in the game have been implemented (to a more- or less-buggy state), now the job is to go back and fix most of the bugs, and add minor features such as individual item behaviours. I’m really enjoying the ride so far and it’s really exciting being able to see the rough outline of what the game is going to be! Hopefully we’ll be ready for some early beta testers early next year some time&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 13 Dec 2022 13:42:16 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://blog.settle-gliese.com/2022/12/13/christmas-update.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.settle-gliese.com/2022/12/13/christmas-update.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Trading, Fire, and Pots</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Hello good people of the internet. It’s been a while since I’ve written one of these, but don’t fear - plenty of hard work has been going on in the background. Now is as good a time as any to fill you in on all the exciting coding adventures I’ve been on. We’ve got a lot to get through so strap yourself in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;trading&quot;&gt;Trading&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s now possible to trade items with your fellow survivors. I feel like there’s still some work to do on the UI but at least the basic functionality is in place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/a-hammer-for-trade.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A Hammer marked for trade&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/trade-1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Speaking to Sam Middleham about what items they have available for trade&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/trade-2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Selecting what trade offer to make&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/trade-3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A trade offer of my hammer for his furniture mover has been made&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/trade-4.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;From Sam’s perspective, he can choose to accept or reject the trade offer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;currency&quot;&gt;Currency&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cultures can now create their own currency, which will make trading much more convenient as there is no back-and-forth if you both agree to the same price. A lot could be written about this, but you didn’t come to this blog to read, did you? Here is an enigmatic screenshot instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/terminal-currency-2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fire&quot;&gt;Fire&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a day/night cycle implemented now. It can be awfully inconvenient to be caught outside of camp after dark - you are likely to be eaten by alien monsters unless you are carrying a torch. The monsters flee from torchlight but you should still find shelter quickly because the torches expire before the end of nightfall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/torch-demonstration.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Here I am bravely leaving camp with the protection of a freshly lit torch&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pots&quot;&gt;Pots&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most exciting of this barrage of updates, it’s now not only possible but positively encouraged for you to decorate pots when you create them. Depending on your talents, you can choose to write a nice description or do a little pixel art, but you will be limited to the colours your culture has the ability to make paints of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/pot-1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A greco-roman style pot&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/pot-2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Or how about something a bit more modern?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/pot-3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A pot being ‘looked’ at&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And for those of you who prefer sharing your wonderful creations on the walls of buildings, you’ll be pleased to know that this is now also possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/graffiti.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A delightful message left for everyone to read&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/graffiti-picture.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;And why not add lifelike portraits to the walls as well?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;other-bits-and-pieces&quot;&gt;Other Bits and Pieces&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve also added the following to the game (in varying states of buggyness)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Summary of events since last login&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fire pits&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;XP system&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Workshop upgrade system&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hunger system (if you are hungry you move slower and your health drops to 1HP)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Domesticated animal breeding&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;thank-you-and-goodbye&quot;&gt;Thank you and Goodbye&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well that’s your blog update. A bit brief on the old words today, but plenty of pictures. If you’ve got any questions or comments I’d love to hear from you in the discord. I’ll update you soon on how the music is going (it’s going well). For the next little bit of time I’m getting the last few killer features into the game - pvp combat, farming, multi-day projects for building (and destroying) walls and gates, and some prompts to encourage you all to get creative. The plan is to get that stuff out in the next couple of weeks, and then spend most of November actually playing my own game and working on all the balance things - tech tree, combat, hunger, and all that good stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until next time, peace out!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 13 Oct 2022 12:16:36 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://blog.settle-gliese.com/2022/10/13/trading-fire-and-pots.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.settle-gliese.com/2022/10/13/trading-fire-and-pots.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Tools for Roleplaying</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Hello friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/vY-3zQ8vjrI&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first video footage taken from the satellite orbiting the planet Gliese has made it back to earth. As you can see, Gliese has been transformed from a lump of rock into a beautiful living planet. It has been seeded with plants and animals, and we even shipped out a few brave volunteers, who are standing around waiting for something to happen. Mysteriously, some things went wrong during the seeding process. There are a lot of bugs and gremlins that have crept in, and who is that guy at 2:30? We’ll have to catch up with him and ask him how he arrived on the planet. Most of these bugs will need to be cleaned up over the following weeks. There are also some important biomes missing, such as the mountains and the mines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;roleplaying&quot;&gt;Roleplaying&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been thinking about different ways to facilitate asynchronous text based roleplaying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;conversation-trees&quot;&gt;Conversation Trees&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it would be nice for players to create ‘conversation trees’ for their characters, which they could use to tell anyone interested about their current activities. Hopefully this will spawn more interaction between people - rather than just standing around being too shy to know what to say to each other, you can get some ice-breakers out of the way and learn what goals each other is pursuing. I’m hoping this will be a good way for experienced players to on-board and engage new arrivals. It should be possible to set quests for each other, and provide a bit of flavour about who these mysterious standing sentinels are if you happen to spawn when nobody else is awake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;players-tables-stages-and-towns&quot;&gt;Players, Tables, Stages, and Towns&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would like to have different objects in the game act as different-sized ‘chat rooms’, to help players speak in private or in groups about things. In Cantr, it can be feel alienating if you are a new arrival in a large and busy town. Hopefully having these different communication channels will help people form more personal relationships. I believe if the most common form of communication moves away from being whole-town chats into smaller forms it may enable people to mantain multiple interesting interactions at once and form more intimate partnerships with their companions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The smallest and most intimate size would be between two people, you can speak to each other in this fashion only when standing next to each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A table would be a chat room of limited size. You would have some ability to get up and sit down from the table whilst the conversation is ongoing, but if everyone gets up from the table at the same time the conversation history is lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A stage would be useable for one character to address many others at the same time. The character stood on the stage could give a passionate speech and the players in the audience could come and go as they please. If there is nobody stood on the stage the conversation history is lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking in main towns would of course still be possible and probably the default way of communication when trying to organise a trade or a whole-town activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;trading&quot;&gt;Trading&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it would be useful to facilitate asynchronous trading. This will hopefully come in two forms - barter, and money. Barter trading will be possible through players marking what items they are holding are available for trade, and other players sending ‘trade offers’ which the first player can accept or reject. Players need to be stood next to each other at the time of acceptance to actually pass the goods between each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With money, trade can go even faster as you can set a price for your goods. I will try to come up with a way for multiple prices to be set, in case there are multiple currencies in circulation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it would be nice for players to create shopfronts so they can trade goods they aren’t hauling around as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you can dream up any interesting forms of chat room or interesting trading methods, feel free to suggest them in the discord. I would love to hear them!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading. Until next time!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 28 Aug 2022 12:16:36 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://blog.settle-gliese.com/2022/08/28/tools-for-roleplaying.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.settle-gliese.com/2022/08/28/tools-for-roleplaying.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Rejected Fauna</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;quick-update&quot;&gt;Quick Update&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hello everyone, it’s time for another update! Over the last two weeks I’ve developed 25 different monsters that will inhabit the mines and try to make your life collecting metals a little bit more difficult. Each monster has a unique ability ranging from ranged and stunning attacks to teleportation - one monster will even attempt to sing a ‘death song’ to you and if you don’t escape or defeat it in ten turns you die.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the next couple of weeks I’ll be working on something completely different - the UI. I’ll be attempting to make the UI more beautiful and ‘game-like’ and will hopefully be able to put all the different menus, pages, and notification boxes into the game. The pixel art for the world is almost finished now, so once the UI is done I’ll be going back to world generation and hopefully be ready to give a quick tour of the planet in around a month from today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;rejected-fauna&quot;&gt;Rejected Fauna&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hello, your friendly neighbourhood pixelartist here to share with you some things that won’t be in Settle Gliese. What you’re going to want to do is navigate over to my special Aseprite file where all my little discarded beasties live and…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/rejected-1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;They needed a place to live you see?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good design IS as much deciding what to cut out as it is deciding what to keep in. So maybe we’ll learn something here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/rejected-2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It all started with these guys, the slime beasts&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was working on a Settle Gliese’s slimes biome and for the first one went down the traditional JRPG style of slime friend, followed by a strange slimy biped and then one that resembles an anglerfish. Harry, Settle Gliese’s creator and mastermind, took one look and decreed the first two simply too cute. I didn’t have the heart to delete them forever, so here we are (anglerfish Slime Beast on the right passed the ugliness test).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/rejected-3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Some things are just not meant to be&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay I have to admit that these monstrous blobs were more like scratch paper monsters than actual attempts at creatures. That jellybean-shaped moose still annoys me. These ones deserved the chopping block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/rejected-4.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The monster in the second row can’t wait to touch you and your weapons (don’t let them, or they’ll rust!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These on the other hand I love! But showing them to Harry was only a repeat of my first slime friend. “No! Too cute! Maybe take out the eyes.” Well, I suppose we are make a rogue-like here, not a JRPG. So maybe you won’t run into all of these fellows, but perhaps you will run into a few of them and when you think “Ah! Why doesn’t it have eyes!?” you have Harry to thank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/rejected-5.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Bleep&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next time I’ll be sharing some of the moodboard behind Settle Gliese’s look as we are coming to the end of the base tileset that will be present on Gliese.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 31 Jul 2022 13:00:36 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://blog.settle-gliese.com/2022/07/31/reject-fauna-of-settle-gliese.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.settle-gliese.com/2022/07/31/reject-fauna-of-settle-gliese.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Biomes With Plants</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Hello everyone. Some of you may have noticed that I didn’t put out a blog post last week, but we’re back this week with lots of exciting updates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;plants&quot;&gt;Plants&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been adding the beautiful art created by our pixel artist into the actual game proper. This is quite a long data-entry heavy process, but it’s made a little more bearable by the beautiful results. I’m about halfway through the total biomes by now. Here are just a few of them:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/misty-tundra.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Misty Tundra&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/inglenook.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Inlenook&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/woneyed.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Woneyed&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/sands.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Wastes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/painforest.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Painforest&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/pits.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Pits&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;animals&quot;&gt;Animals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work is continuing on getting interesting animals into the world. I have some nice behaviours coded but will hold off on showing you any gifs until the animal tiles are done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;preditors&quot;&gt;Preditors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are various bear- and wolf-like creatures now in the world. Some of these will aggressively attack and chase any humans or livestock that they encounter, and others will more cautiously stalk their prey. The stalkers will not attack a large group of humans, preferring to wait until someone is isolated and vulnerable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;prey&quot;&gt;Prey&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are animals for you to hunt. Most of these flee when you get within a certain distance from them so to catch them will require cunning or teamwork. Some of them, like deer, will just run away from you, and others, like racoons and rabbits, will flee up the nearest tree, or down the nearest rabbit hole, where they will be out of your reach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;working-animals&quot;&gt;Working Animals&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are animals for you to work. Horses, reindeer, camels, cows, sheep, and goats. These will only be available to you if you spawn in certain biomes (for example, the reindeer are only for taiga based survivors). Some of them can pull wagons and some of them can be ridden with saddles. These animals will make it possible to live nomadically, and many of them will seriously change how many resources you are able to carry long distances, but you will only get them if you embark to one of the most difficult areas of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;whats-next&quot;&gt;What’s Next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the next couple of weeks I’ll be coding the mines. I’m hoping in this time I’ll be able to have interesting terrains and dangerous creatures. The deeper in the mine you travel the more dangerous the monsters but also the more rich the rewards will be. Then at the end of July hopefully all of the biome and animal art will be finished by our artist, and then I will go back to that and finish the second half of the biomes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 17 Jul 2022 08:00:36 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://blog.settle-gliese.com/2022/07/17/biomes-with-plants.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.settle-gliese.com/2022/07/17/biomes-with-plants.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Procedural Generation of Biomes</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Hello friends. This week was quite eventful. The most exciting (and by that I mean terrifying) moment was definitely when someone tried to smash down the front door to my apartment whilst I was sat at my desk working. They managed to get the door partially open but luckily we had the chain on and they didn’t get through that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/jonny.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I argued through the door with them for a while whilst my girlfriend called the cops. After a while of asking them to kindly fuck off they asked to just come in and collect their clothes. I told them we’d in fact been the sole occupants of this flat for five years. It took a lot of convincing for them to understand they had got the wrong apartment but eventually I pointed out the unique graffitti next to the door and without so much as an apology they conceded I was correct and went upstairs to smash another door in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually the cops came, the crazy person was sat on a bench in the street nearby. We gave statements, a locksmith came to repair the door… It turns out it was just some very confused person thinking they were breaking into their own apartment because they forgot their keys…? Well, I guess this kind of stuff occasionally happening is the price you pay for living in a busy street in Berlin. Will they come back and try to break in again? Tune in next week to find out. Anyway, forgive me the brief interlude into my real life - the real excitement this week came from the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;daynight-cycle&quot;&gt;Day/Night cycle&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, I animated the day/night cycle. Currently one day = 1 hour. There’s 20 minutes of night, 10 minutes of sunrise, 20 minutes of day, 10 minutes of sunset. Night time will be dangerous so make sure you’ve got walls and fires set up before your first nightfall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/sunrise.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The sun rising on the planet Gliese (sped up)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;animals&quot;&gt;Animals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to spend a few days on something that has been worrying me - animals. In the alpha, animals are not visible to the player and you can only interact with them by clicking a ‘hunt’ button. For the next iteration of the game, I want fully visible animals with ‘intelligent’ behaviour - some of them will flee from you, others will hunt you, and if you’re lucky some will fling dung at you from the treetops. I was a bit worried about coding this, so I decided to have a quick look at the problem before starting on the biomes to see what was achievable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily for me, the hard parts have already been done for me. I’m using the amazing open source project &lt;a href=&quot;https://ondras.github.io/rot.js/hp/&quot;&gt;rot.js&lt;/a&gt; to make complicated things like pathfinding and line of sight easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m pleased to say it went pretty well. The animals will behave ‘turn based’, similar to traditional roguelikes - meaning they will only take an action in response to you. If there is more than one character on the screen at once, they will only behave in response to the character closest to them. I made a simple creature that comes out at night and hunts down humans, and then it flees in the daylight. For the gifs that follow I disabled night time so you can actually see him come towards me. He looks like a large naked man at the moment - don’t worry, that won’t make it into the final game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here he is running towards me:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/night-stalker.gif&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey come here, I just want to talk&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here he is running away&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/fleeing.gif&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Run away!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;biomes&quot;&gt;Biomes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/biomes-1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Mock ups of the biomes - each square of colour translates to a different pixel art tile&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have 45 different biomes to generate. Each comes with its own set of challenges but in general these are what I want to try to achieve:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Objects which overflow from one panel will be shown on the next panel (no ‘half’ trees)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Some things are ‘fully generated’ patterns such as grass clumps, magma lines&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Others are ‘rubber stamp’ style shapes such as trees, which are repeated across a panel placed seemingly at random&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Others have a set of possible stamp shapes, the full list of which can be generated by code&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Some items take the shape of randomly curved lines, linking up other shapes or points on the map&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m going to share with you how I’m trying to create these. This week we’ll start with the basics of terrain generation. None-technical readers beware - you might want to skip to the end of this blog post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tundra&quot;&gt;Tundra&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start off by trying to generate a pattern that looks a bit like the ‘tundra’ biome shown above. We start with a simplex noise generator. This generates basically a 2D array of random numbers between -1 and 1. I created an array the height and width of one panel, then converted the result into tiles and displayed them. Any number &amp;gt; 0 is ‘empty’, anything &amp;lt; 0 is ‘water’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;// generating a 2D array of noise
export function drawNoise() {
    const coords = [];

    const noise = new Noise.Simplex();

    for(var x=0; x &amp;lt; PANEL_WIDTH; x++) {
        for(var y=0; y &amp;lt; PANEL_HEIGHT; y++) {
            const noiseValue = noise.get(y, x);

            if (!coords[x]) {
                coords[x] = []
            }

            coords[x][y] = noiseValue;
        }
    }

    return coords;
}

// Then for each tile in the map, we colour it in
if (noise[rowIndex][columnIndex] &amp;gt; 0) {
    tile.index = tileMap[&apos;EMPTY&apos;];
} else {
    tile.index = tileMap[&apos;WATER&apos;]; 
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which comes out with this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/total-noise.png&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Random noise&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the cool thing about simplex noise, as opposed to just using something like &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Math.random()&lt;/code&gt;, is that you can play around with the values you put in the get different ‘types’ of noise. Lets say instead of the above snippet, we divide the x and y coordinates of the noise by 10 - this effectively ‘zooms in’ on the noise, which is called (I think) increasing the &lt;a href=&quot;https://leatherbee.org/index.php/2018/10/24/perlin-and-simplex-noise/&quot;&gt;‘amplitude’&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;const noiseValue = noise.get(y/10, x/10);&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blobs.png&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;‘blobby’ noise (not the technical term)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take a look at the tundra biome again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/tundra.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you look closely, what we basically have are large blobs of black and large blobs of red, but they are faded into each other. So we just need to add a fade effect to this and we’ll have something pretty close. The way to do that is by combining multiple sets of noise with different blob sizes. We call this combining different &lt;a href=&quot;https://clockworkchilli.com/blog/6_procedural_textures_in_javascript&quot;&gt;‘octaves’&lt;/a&gt; of noise. I had fun twiddling the noise strengths for a while until I came up with this&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;const noiseOne = drawNoise(20, 35);
const noiseTwo = drawNoise(1, 1);
const noiseThree = drawNoise(10, 10);

let finalNoise = noiseOne.map((noiseArray, x) =&amp;gt; {
    return noiseArray.map((noiseValue, y) =&amp;gt; (noiseValue + noiseTwo[x][y]))
})

finalNoise = finalNoise.map((noiseArray, x) =&amp;gt; {
    return noiseArray.map((noiseValue, y) =&amp;gt; (noiseValue + noiseThree[x][y]))
})

if (finalNoise[rowIndex][columnIndex] &amp;gt; 0.5) {
    tile.index = tileMap[&apos;EMPTY&apos;];
} else {
    tile.index = tileMap[&apos;WATER&apos;];
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/tundra-noise.png&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Three octaves of noise&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there we have it. By playing around with the numbers passed into the noise generator, we can come up with a surprising variety of different types of noise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tiling-noise&quot;&gt;Tiling Noise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next problem with this noise is when you move to the north and generate a new panel, the new noise bears no relation to the previous noise. You could have a large empty clump on one panel that seems to end in a solid vertical line, as on the next panel it’s all a different colour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/non-tiled-noise.gif&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Changing panels feels clunky because the noise doesn’t tile&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to get my noise to tile. First I went off on a bit of a tangent here taking my noise to another dimension and trying to generate 4D noise and map my 2D noise onto a &lt;a href=&quot;https://ronvalstar.nl/creating-tileable-noise-maps&quot;&gt;‘4D hypercube’&lt;/a&gt;. I can confirm for any of you wondering that this does indeed create tiling noise, but in fact that’s not what I’m looking for. If you look at this image from the 4D hypercube tutorial you’ll see why:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/hypercube.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The noise tiles in a regular and predictable fashion, but that’s not really what I’m looking for. I want truly random noise that flows into itself from one panel to the next. The correct solution for me was to actually just generate more noise - rather than a square of noise 48 wide and 25 high, we need to generate noise the height and width of the whole planet, and zoom in on the panel we’re looking at. Then when we move to the next panel, we just change the zoom location and the noise will flow from one area to the next smoothly. This was a lot easier to achieve than playing around with hypercubes and the good news is I don’t actually have to generate the full noise each time as long as I generate the noise from the correct area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;const coords = [];

const noise = makeNoise2D();

const startX = position.x * PANEL_WIDTH;
const endX = startX + PANEL_WIDTH;

const startY = position.y * PANEL_HEIGHT;
const endY = startY + PANEL_HEIGHT;

for(var x=0; x &amp;lt; PANEL_WIDTH; x++) {
    for(var y=0; y &amp;lt; PANEL_HEIGHT; y++) {
        const noiseValue = noise((startY + y)/powerValue, (startX + x)/secondPowerValue);

        if (!coords[x]) {
            coords[x] = []
        }

        coords[x][y] = noiseValue;
    }
}

return coords;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/tiling-2d-huge.gif&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Here I can walk around and the noise flows naturally accross panels&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bonus-content&quot;&gt;Bonus content&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading. I have made a little more progress than this but the article is rather long and technical already so I’ll stop here for this week. As a reward for those of you who scrolled all the way to the bottom of the page, here are the rest of the biomes as I originally came up with them a few months ago. Each of those square blobs will be translated into a beautiful pixel art tile over the coming weeks and months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/biomes-2.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/biomes-3.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/biomes-4.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/biomes-5.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jun 2022 16:00:36 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://blog.settle-gliese.com/2022/06/24/procedural-generation-of-biomes.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.settle-gliese.com/2022/06/24/procedural-generation-of-biomes.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Cramped Apartments and Space Stations</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-settle-gliese-backstory&quot;&gt;The Settle Gliese Backstory&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Settle Gliese is set in a dystopian future where most inhabitants on earth are kept in dingy apartments with nothing to do except play on their computers and watch TV all day. Some of these understandably bored individuals find themselves targeted by adverts that offer a way out. They are tempted into joining a twisted gameshow - one in which they’re transported to a terraformed planet and dropped off with no supplies, all for the entertainment of people back on earth. It’s the most ambitious and expensive reality TV show ever, organised by one of the megacorporations that controls all of the resources and factories. How will the people get on in the new planet? Will they learn to work together and form a better society than the one they left behind? Or will the desperations of a life without modern comforts drive them towards violence? And what about this shadowy megacorp? What do the people working for them think about all this? And how exactly did they manage to terraform this planet just for entertainment purposes?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re trying to introduce the player into this world and get them asking these questions as they play through the tutorial. One way we’re achieving this is through the size and shape of the rooms - we want small, cramped rooms connected with long tight corridors. Another vital part is of course the pixel art. This week I’ve been integrating the new pixel art into the tutorial, and I’m very pleased with the result so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-dingy-apartment&quot;&gt;The Dingy Apartment&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/bedroom.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;You don’t want to know where the toilet is…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The apartment is very small and you can’t see anything outside it. The door looks very heavy and the player is unable to walk through it. The chair in the apartment doubles as storage, which is a smart design choice in such a tiny room. There is nothing for the player to do except start up his computer and browse aimlessly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-space-station&quot;&gt;The Space Station&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/spaceship.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Who would’ve thought an office floating in space could be so boring?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The space station has long bare corridors and spartan offices. It is a bit tired looking, with little notes stuck up in front of some of the office doors. You can see some barrels and pipes attached to the outer hull in silhouette - clearly it was built without beauty in mind. Like in any corporation, there seems to be a hierarchy here. Some of the people you talk to go to lengths to show you they are more important than you, whereas others seem to be more friendly and less formal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/choose-embark.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Whatever architect designed this place needs a paycut&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-shuttle&quot;&gt;The Shuttle&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/spacepod.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey, you look like someone I know…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The shuttle taking you to the planet is small and clunky looking - it is more cube shaped than the sleek rocket designs of earlier space shuttles. Here you will meet your comrades if you choose to embark somewhere new.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, that about  sums up what I’ve been working on this week - now let’s hear from our guest writer, who has been labouring under a hot Berlin sun (I let them pick their own title for their section this week…)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bloggy-bit-sry-its-not-much-i-cant-think-of-anything-else-to-say-cos-hot&quot;&gt;bloggy bit sry it’s not much, i can’t think of anything else to say cos hot&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hello from your local pixel artist! I have been busy these weeks working on some of the rarer and more far-flung flora and fauna on Gliese. The places that won’t make up the majority of arable land but will hopefully be special places to travel through and explore. I kind of don’t want to spoil these locations (and you’d want to chart biomes like “The Slimes”, “Crunchy Forest” and “Gumbo Rumblings” yourself right?) so today instead I’ll share some rejected pixel art.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/experimentbloggy.png&quot; width=&quot;340&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Okay, who keeps putting holes in my dang fences?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something we wanted to explore with what’s possible to make in Gliese is limitations that resources would have on what you make and how it looks. Regionally accessible dyestuffs for example could tell the story of how far you had to travel and how many friends you had to make along the way to have your fancy blue and yellow fence for example. And as you travel you can expect to run into different cultures and architecture arising from different locations. The above ideas were initial explorations of this idea but weren’t in keeping with the style we are going for so we won’t be using them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I leave you with these &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nationalgeographic.com/magazine/article/searching-for-californias-mysterious-albino-redwood&quot;&gt;gorgeous albino pines&lt;/a&gt; photographed by Natgeo. While you’re out there exploring Gliese keep an eye out for these arboreal ghosts&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s all for this week folks! Check in next time when I’ll introduce you to the wonderful world of procedural world generation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jun 2022 16:00:36 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://blog.settle-gliese.com/2022/06/24/cramped-apartments-and-space-stations.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.settle-gliese.com/2022/06/24/cramped-apartments-and-space-stations.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Journeying to Gliese</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;lets-journey-together&quot;&gt;Let’s Journey Together&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hello again friends. This week work continued on the tutorial. I hope to have most of the functionality finished by the end of next week so I can start on the fun stuff - generating the beautiful new biomes, animals, and tech tree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;graceful-long-potato-shaped-people&quot;&gt;Graceful Long Potato Shaped People&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One important but slightly problematic task I did this week was converting the current game engine from 16px square tiles to 16px x 24px rectangles. Unfortunately I’m still loading in the old tileset because the new one is not ready, which has lead to this interesting ‘stretched potato person’ effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/stretched-potato.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Is it just me or is something strange happening?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;space-tiles&quot;&gt;Space tiles&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next week I will try to replace these glorious stretched potatos with something from the new artwork. Check out these tiles we’ve been creating&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/walls.png&quot; width=&quot;200&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Walls of various sorts&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The space station will be owned and operated by a mega corporation, who are sadistically sending you to the planet for their latest reality TV show. We want the space station to strike a balance between ‘futuristic cutting-edge technology’ and ‘shabby souless corporate office’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/tileset-ship.png&quot; width=&quot;220&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Space walls and silhouetted space station parts&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;draggable-grid-layout&quot;&gt;Draggable Grid Layout&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/transport-tycoon.jpeg&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Transport tycoon was an early adopter of this revolutionary layout style&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am toying with the idea of making the various screens in the game draggable, resizable, and hide-able. Depending on what is happening in the game you might want a few different menus up. When in a deep conversation, for example, you might want a small game screen and an enlarged dialogue screen; when you’re crafting it can be helpful to have your inventory and the crafting screen both showing; and so on. Let me know what you think of this idea in the discord.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/draggable-grid.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A draggable grid offers the most layout flexibility&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conversation-trees&quot;&gt;Conversation Trees&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you first arrive on the space station orbiting the planet Gliese, you have a conversation with the captain, who fills you in on what you’ll be getting up to when you arrive on the planet. We need more versatile ways for characters to communicate asyncronously, and allowing players to create their own dialogue trees would be one way to accomplish this, so this screen may be used for more than just the tutorial. In the future I will remove the purple and orange boxes from the dialogue and go with a more dignified white-on-black design. Adding some logic to convert *asterisks* to &lt;em&gt;italic&lt;/em&gt; would be a nice improvement as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/dialogue-tree.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A conversation between a new recruit and the captain of the space station&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;generated-embark-lobby&quot;&gt;Generated Embark Lobby&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once a character has been introduced to the world by the captain of the space station, they will be sent off to either join an existing group of established settlers or, if they are feeling particularly reckless, a new group. Rather than displaying a static menu showing which groups are available, I thought it would be more fun to generate rooms for the player to join. There will be a control panel in each room that will show a descripition of the group you are considering joining, and some furniture and decorations. The rooms will be sized according to how many players are currently in the group. Players on the planet will be able to edit their control panel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/embark-lobby.png&quot; height=&quot;650&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This wooden space station with beautiful sand flooring is only temporary&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;embark-options&quot;&gt;Embark Options&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a character is ambitious, the option is open for them to create their own embark group. The creator will have the chance to choose the biome the embark group joins, and give a brief description in which they can describe their goals for the group. It would also be useful for the creator to specify how close to other groups they would like to be - some groups might like the challenge of being completely isolated, whereas others will aim to establish relationships with nearby groups as quickly as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/create-embark-group.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A new embark group form&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another option is to show the user the full map of the planet and highlight which areas fit their current search parameters - if that’s done, users could even choose a specific place to embark to. I’m a little reluctant to do that, however, because the idea of players not knowing the world map and having to discover it as a player group appeals to me. It would also be open to abuse from griefers and metagamers. Let me know what you would rather have in the discord channel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading folks, I’ll see you again next week!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jun 2022 12:20:37 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://blog.settle-gliese.com/2022/06/16/embarking-to-gliese.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.settle-gliese.com/2022/06/16/embarking-to-gliese.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Growing Gliese’s Forests, From the Roots Up</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;this-weeks-update&quot;&gt;This Week’s Update&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hello friends and welcome to this week’s update. The true work has started in earnest now and I’ve started on an exciting and vital aspect of the game world. Read on to find out what - but first, the next section will be guest written by our talented pixel artist auilix&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;growing-glieses-forests-from-the-roots-up&quot;&gt;Growing Gliese’s Forests, From the Roots Up&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/early-pixel-art.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The forests of the artist’s youth&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I admit, I thought that developing the forests of a planet through pixel art would be an easy first step into Settle Gliese’s generated alien world. I love trees and the comfort of forests and, armed with references and scholarly articles (check out these &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.indefenseofplants.com/blog/2017/10/31/the-first-trees-ripped-themselves-apart-to-grow&quot;&gt;prehistoric trees&lt;/a&gt;!, I started off emulating tilesets of the trees from games gone by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/side-view.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Ah, repeating tree tiles as far as they eye can see&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going in this direction was hearkening back to my own history with older consoles and JRPGs but was quite out of touch with the built up history of roguelikes and their much more constrained visual language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/roguelike.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The original Rogue (1980)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/dwarf-fortress.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A forest in Dwarf Fortress (2002)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even modern roguelikes tend to use limited sprites or ASCII art to evoke their worlds and inhabitants, resulting in a unique look and mood. With this in mind, I turned towards pictographic and logographic languages as an inspiration and began to draw up more conceptual representations of trees. Deconstructing trees and pushing symbolic meaning in the limited constraints of 16 x 24 pixel tiles let to some crop circle-ish results:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/iconic.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The top right tree partially inspired by a blanket my mom crocheted for me&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think my personal favourite of this series was on the middle row on the right which looks like it could be related to the Nazca geoglyphs of South America. Though these trees were recognisable enough, the main problem was that they’d be too limited in scope to be able to express Settle Gliese’s 40+ different planned biomes with that much diversity. So it was back to the Aesprite board to develop something both symbolic but not too pared down, with room for lots of biodiversity and personality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/final.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Please excuse the in-development wanderers who are modelling the forest for us&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These circuit board-esque trees hit the right spot for us. They look like they could be of some future age while at the same time wouldn’t look that out of place on an illuminated manuscript. And their complexity feels right for the look and feel of changing regions as you move throughout the world, while not straying too far from the look of its genre. The next step for me will be expanding this design to flora and fauna and fully visualising Gliese’s first biomes. More on that soon!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introducing-players-to-the-world&quot;&gt;Introducing Players to the World&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for that, auilix! Whilst they’ve been busy working on that, I can share for the first time in a world exclusive what exciting things I’ve been working on this week. That’s right guys - it’s the tutorial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://giphy.com/embed/nbNWgtnMgIYpUSy3e9&quot; width=&quot;480&quot; height=&quot;327&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;giphy-embed&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://giphy.com/gifs/fallontonight-jimmy-fallon-tonight-show-nbNWgtnMgIYpUSy3e9&quot;&gt;via GIPHY&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps not the most thrilling for the readers of this blog, but an important part of the game. In the alpha, you were simply dropped on an alien planet and left to get on with things. Lots of players, especially those new to the text based roleplaying genre, would simply run off into the wilderness before speaking to anyone and get lost out there until they inevitably starved to death. I decided to provide some context to the game to help new playeres out - maybe they will still run off into the wild with their first character, but they will at least understand what they should be trying to do when creating their second. Rather than just show them a wall of text, I decided an interactive tutorial might be more entertaining. I’m about halfway done with it, and wanted to share my progress with you dear reader. The artwork is not ready so you’ll have to use your imagination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/startup.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When you first start a new game, you will find your character alone in a tiny apartment here on earth&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/startup.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The door will be locked. Eventually you will figure out the only thing you can do is sit at your desk and turn your computer on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/pong.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;For a while, you will entertain yourself by playing pong, or perhaps some other moderately entertaining task&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/informatic.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/informatic.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Click on the image to see it full size&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then you will be interrupted with an advert. If you press escape, you can return to the safety of your apartment. But for those brave (or bored) enough to press any key, will be taken to the ‘registration form’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/registration.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/registration.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A fully filled out registration form. Click on the image again to see it full size&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This page is intended to get players thinking about the personality of their character. Players new to text based roleplaying games tend to invent flawless individuals which can be uninteresting to interact with, so I have included some questions like ‘what are your weaknesses’ to guide these players towards making more nuanced characters. I had great fun randomly generating answers. Once this page is filled out, you are taken to a spaceship en route to the planet, where you will be shown a bit more about the world, and choose who to embark with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me know what you think about the character creation page - if you have any good answers to the questions, they’ll be added to the auto generator and appear in the final game!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next week I’ll be working on what happens when you’ve submitted your form and find yourself on a spaceship heading straight for the planet Gliese. You’ll meet a couple of interesting characters who explain the strange world you’ve found yourself in further.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jun 2022 14:56:46 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://blog.settle-gliese.com/2022/06/05/growing-glieses-forests.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.settle-gliese.com/2022/06/05/growing-glieses-forests.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How to Generate a World</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;this-weeks-update&quot;&gt;This Week’s Update&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hello friends. This week has been a pretty exciting time for the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First but by no means least, after some months of paperwork ping pong I have received the contract for the funding application, so fingers crossed I might actually receive the first installment some time soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For most of the week I’ve been working on the prologue, which has involved building a terminal emulator, and building a sort of ‘staged scene’ in the game world. There’s still plenty of work to do here but it’s been fun getting my hands dirty. I’ll try not to show too many spoilers, but here’s one little screen shot which doesn’t give too much away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/terminal.png&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Now you too, can be a hacker&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pixel-art&quot;&gt;Pixel Art&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/warmup-septembitchall.png&quot; height=&quot;300&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Some pink items&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/warmup-froggypractice.png&quot; height=&quot;192&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Various frogs of different types&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Auilix, the pixel artist (follow them &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/auilix&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;), started off the week getting into pixel art. Drawing on a small top-down scale with a limited palette is more puzzle working and problem solving than illustration usually is, so warm ups are necessary. Saultoon’s excellent &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/c/saultoons&quot;&gt;channel&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/septembit&quot;&gt;Septembit challenge&lt;/a&gt; were a perfect jumping-off point and check out these 16 x 16 frogs as a bonus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After some design exploration and palette building, we decided to go with a rectangular 16 x 24 pixel tile over the 16 x 16 tiles we used in the alpha for Settle Gliese. A vertical rectangle shape is more ‘human’ shaped than a square, and I think it makes the sprites seem more mature and less potato shaped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/pixelexperiments1a.png&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Potato people and square objects&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/pixelexperiments2a.png&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Long graceful, people-shaped people&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a consequence there will be more tiles on a panel, which I don’t think is a bad thing. Let me know what you think!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And for all you dead by daylight fans, here is some dead by daylight fan art in the new style:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/lildbd.png&quot; height=&quot;72&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Coming soon to a screen near you - Dead By Daylight the Roguelike&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;game-design&quot;&gt;Game Design&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve also been working a lot on the game design and have made some pretty big decisions that I think will improve how the game plays. There’s still a lot that will go into this and everything’s a work in progress. If you have any thoughts or suggestions about these feel free to share in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://discord.gg/h9sCtUfhhW&quot;&gt;discord&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mountains-into-mazes&quot;&gt;Mountains into Mazes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mountains represented a serious barrier for early humans, and impeded migration to such an extent that in some places different cultures, languages, and even races would develop on either side of the mountain range. Pretty cool, right? I want this to arise in the game, but how to achieve this in an interesting way? We could always force characters to move very slowly through mountain regions, or add a chance of them dying, but I wanted characters to feel that desperation of being lost and stuck halfway up a mountain and these options didn’t quite give that feeling. But I had another idea - we could turn the mountains into huge multi-panel mazes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/maze-mountain.png&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;What a maze looks like&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this way players can cross if they’re really desperate, brave, or foolish, but I hope most players will be sufficiently put off. Hopefully this is a nice way of translating a real world problem into a ‘game-like’ problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mines-into-dungeons&quot;&gt;Mines into Dungeons&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mines were also very dangerous places back in the day, so much so that the best way to get rich from mining was to persuade someone else to do it for you. In the alpha of the game mining was simply a case of walking up to a deposit of some stone or ore, and clicking the ‘gather’ button.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/alpha-mine.png&quot; height=&quot;150&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;An familiar scene&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted it to be more dangerous, to force players to make the same kind of risk reward calculations that early humans must have considered when entering a mine. My first idea was to make players ‘dig’ a mine, and on each dig there was a percentage chance of the mine collapsing and the player dying. Then I realised what countless other game designers must have realised before me, we can represent the danger of a mine in a much more entertaining way by turning them into dungeons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/mock-mine.png&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A very bare bones mock up of a mine-dungeon&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A player can enter a mine and battle their way through monsters if they want to find the riches buried therein. Or if they value their life, they can persuade other players to explore the mines for them. I hope this will be a nice system for giving newspawns a fun task, as town leaders can persuade them to go spelunking on their behalf.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;multiple-metals&quot;&gt;Multiple Metals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A final problem I had with the alpha was that once you had discovered bronze and made all bronze items, there wasn’t much further tech tree to go, but before you discovered bronze there also wasn’t much to do. My first thought was to simply make discovering bronze harder and expand the early game tech tree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/scrap-metal.jpeg&quot; height=&quot;300&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A bunch of useless metal&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I think a better solution is to have multiple new metals made up of two or more ores, with varying rarity. The rarer metals will of course produce to stronger weapons, armour, and tools. This I think should be a lot easier to balance than the ‘just bronze’ route, and with the best of metals only available if you mine ores coming from opposite sides of the planet, it will strongly incentivise long trade routes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;apothecaries-and-brainchip-upgrades&quot;&gt;Apothecaries and Brainchip Upgrades&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as metals, we can apply a similar principle to the creation of tonics and the upgrading of brainchips. Local plants or rare minerals can provide small upgrades, but for the most powerful effects you’ll need to swap plants that only occur on the other side of the planet. With plants, players will need ‘local knowledge’ - you can only harvest the valuable parts of the plant if you were born in that region. In this way long distance trade or tyranical empires will be the only methods of obtaining the most powerful in game items.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-generate-a-planet&quot;&gt;How to Generate a Planet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of you may be interested in how the planet Gliese was generated, so I will add a quick lowdown of how I did it here. In summary - someone else did it for me. I used the brilliant open source project &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Mindwerks/worldengine&quot;&gt;Mindwerks WorldEngine&lt;/a&gt;, which generates a full little world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ancient_map_seed1.png&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The worlds are generated using plate techtonics, erosion, rain shadows, holdridge life zone models (whatever they are) and more.  I generated a number of little worlds until I found one I liked the look of. You choose the size of the world, and it generates elevation, precipitation, temperature, biome, and ocean maps as images. I then wrote a small program which reads each of these images and saves the data into a database. Not sure what I mean by that? Take for example this heat map&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/heat-map.png&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The average temperatures of a generated planet&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are seven colours on this map which represent seven temperatures. My program would look at each pixel, convert its colour into the temperature range (from 1-7), and save this data under the pixel’s position. Once I’d done this for every pixel, I had the full world in a database. Each of those pixels is one panel in Settle Gliese. Generating the terrain for the panels, including cliffs, rivers, and coastlines, was a little more complicated. Maybe I’ll write some more about that another time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading, I’ll see you again next week!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jun 2022 14:56:46 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://blog.settle-gliese.com/2022/06/05/how-to-generate-a-world.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.settle-gliese.com/2022/06/05/how-to-generate-a-world.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
